<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An advertisement, relating to lead-sheathing in general, and particularly that upon the Worcester bound for Guinea, a ship newly sheathed, and now lying in Mr. Newman's dock in Lymehouse Hole, but goes out in two or three days time, 20 of November. 1699.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16705</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886626</idno>
  <idno type="VID">187553</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240896323</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A618</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.7[124]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226293</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886626</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99886626e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16705)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187553)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C8:1[127])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An advertisement, relating to lead-sheathing in general, and particularly that upon the Worcester bound for Guinea, a ship newly sheathed, and now lying in Mr. Newman's dock in Lymehouse Hole, but goes out in two or three days time, 20 of November. 1699.</title>
                  <author>Hale, Charles, Mr.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-Rom, 1996).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sheet-lead --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Shipbuilding --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:187553:1"/>
            <head>An Advertisement, Relating to Lead-Sheathing in General, and particularly That upon the <hi>Worcester</hi> bound for <hi>Guinea,</hi> a Ship new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sheathed, and now lying in Mr. <hi>Newman</hi>'s Dock in <hi>Lymehouse-Hole,</hi> but goes out in two or three days time, 20 of <hi>November.</hi> 1699.</head>
            <p>THIS Ship is Sheathed with Lead from the Keel up as high as any Wood-shea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing goes, where, upon a bare View, any one that is unprejudiced must be convinc'd of its Excellency and Goodness in Preferrence to that of Wood, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out recourse to Experience, which has abundantly justified it in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, <hi>viz.</hi> better Preservation of the <hi>Plank, Seams, Ironwork, and benefit of Sailing, as well as certain Security from the Worm, upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 30 <hi>Ships,</hi> against all the false and ridiculous Stories its Enemies have formerly raised against it, as Mr. <hi>Hale</hi> has often Proved, Published, and Challenged any one fairly to Answer that can; but they wisely decline that, knowing it will not bear a Publick Test, but still go on with their positive Averments, and private Insinuations with their Friends, to raise new Stories as the old ones are baffled, as they have lately done, That it did rot and decay the Okam in the Seams, which was never heard of before, for that in truth it preserves it longer, as he has proved from Reason and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in the <hi>Antilopes Evidence,</hi> &amp;c. which story being new invented, to make it necessary (if Owners will Sheath with Lead) to strip the Sheathing every Voyage, that the charge thereof may make them weary of it: Mr. <hi>Hale</hi> (to put an end to these Tricks) was advised to address himself at a General Court to the <hi>English East India Company,</hi> as great Patrones of our Trade, and Improvements, which he did by a Proposal of Lead-sheathing, as an Invention of great Use and Benefit to the Publick, as well as those that used it, desiring they would be pleased to take the same into their Consideration, and upon due Examination and Enquiry into the Merit and Goodness thereof, in preference to that of Wood hitherto used, and of the Truth and Validity of the Objections made against it) if they should find the thing it self deserved it, that they would be pleased to give it their Countenance and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement accordingly.</p>
            <p>This Proposal they referred to the Consideration of their Court of Directors, 2 <hi>Feb.</hi> last, who having taken time enough fully to inform themselves, and to consider thereof (not thinking it reasonable to impose the Lead-sheathing upon any one) 21 <hi>Sept.</hi> last, were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to make an Order, That it be left indifferently to all Owners of Ships to be taken into their Service, to Sheath them with Lead or Board, as they think fit; but that it he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to them to prefer Lead Sheathing, and that the Companies Husband [having discovered great prejudice against it] be enjoyned to be indifferent in the Matter, and to shew their Satisfaction therein, and full Approbation thereof, for the encouragement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the 18 of <hi>Octob.</hi> last, They ordered the <hi>May-Flower,</hi> which they had newly bought (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the first Ship they had of their own, and which they designed to remain long a Coaster in the Indies) to be Sheathed with Lead, and that the care be committed to Mr. <hi>Hale</hi> to have the Seams well Caulked; the Rudder Irons Sound and well Wrought, and all the Iron work parcelled himself, which their Husband was not a ware of: So that it is to be hoped its Enemies will now think themselves obliged to acquiess at last, after a determination of the Point by such Judges, that must be satisfied upon a Full and Impartial enquiry into the Truth, and Merit of the Matter before them, and that the Shipwrights will undertake for the well Caulking of the Seames, and due parcelling of the Ironwork (that they shall at least, last as long under a Lead, as under a Wood-sheathing) for the future, that they may be trusted therewith as formerly, which otherwise they cannot be, if they shall have it in their Power to charge the ill effects of their own wilful or careless neglect of the well performing so necessary a Work for the Ships Health, upon the Leadsheathing as the cause thereof.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, that upon searching the <hi>May-Flower,</hi> to fit her out for their Service they found her Bottom eaten with the Worm, and so rotten that they were forced to lay her a side, and ordered their Husband to look out for another, who knowing she was to be Sheathed with Lead, delayed the time, and at last pretending he could find none in the River that was so fit for their Service, as a new Ship already Sheathed with Wood upon the Stocks, and her Voyage requiring dispatch, they bought this Ship. He props'd one Wood Sheathed-Ship to them before, but it seems they did not like her, and he was resolv'd they should have no other, wherein their Husband has shewn his Cuning to serve his Friends, what cause soever his Masters have to thank him for it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hale</hi> lives at the <hi>Mill'd-Lead-sign,</hi> in <hi>Orange-Street</hi> by <hi>Red-Lyon-Square,</hi> who undertakes Covering of Churches, Houses, and all Work wherein Sheet Lead is used, as well as Sheathing Ships, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having able Plumbers and Workmen, sufficient to perform the same: And may be heard of also at <hi>John</hi>'s in <hi>Burchen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> or <hi>Batson</hi>'s Coffee-houses.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>